Diego Grados

I am a bioscience engineer and applied statistician using interdisciplinary approaches to address sustainable development challenges in agriculture, focused on soil-plant-atmosphere interactions, agroecosystems analysis, and remote sensing. During my involvement in international research projects with multidisciplinary partners, I have demonstrated excellent teamwork and communication skills. I am proficient in programming languages for data-processing applications and process-based modelling. I have also cultivated my enthusiasm for the creation of integrated assessments, focusing on the data science to translate information into knowledge.

Personal Data

Address

Phone

Email diegogradosb@agro.au.dk

Web https://diegogradosb.github.io ORCID https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5548-3204

Relevant Experience

SEP 2020 -PRESENT

Postdoctoral Researcher - AARHUS UNIVERSITY, Aarhus - Denmark

Climate and Water - Agroecology Department - Faculty of Technical Sciences

- Mitigation strategies of greenhouse gas emissions (field experiments, data-driven applications, process-based models).
- International collaboration projects: PROENV, MACSUR SciPol.
- Dissemination of results in seminars, workshops, peer-reviewed journals and international conferences.
- Mentoring and supervision of MSc and PhD thesis students.

References: Prof. Dr. Diego ABALOS, Prof. Dr. Jørgen Eivind OLESEN

JAN 2020 -MAR 2020

Researcher - KU LEUVEN, Leuven - Belgium

Mechatronics, Biostatistics and Sensors - Biosystems Department - Faculty of Bioscience Engineering

- Developing of multi-target and system modeling methodologies for the agroecosystems' sustainability assessment.
- Dissemination of research results in workshops and peer-reviewed journals. Mentoring of PhD thesis students.

APR 2016 -DEC 2019

PhD Researcher

- Developing of multi-target and system modeling methodologies for the agroecosystems' sustainability assessment.

- Dissemination of results in seminars, workshops, peer-reviewed journals and international conferences.
- Mentoring and supervision of BSc and MSc thesis students in Peru (UNALM and UNCP) and Belgium (KU Leuven).

Reference: Prof. Dr. Eddie Schrevens

NOV 2014 -APR 2019

Research Assistant - *VLIR/UOS-UNALM PROJECT*, Lima - Peru *Strengthening of Smallholder Horticultural Systems Subproject*

- Co-leading the study of soil-crop-environment interactions in the Peruvian Coastal Desert.
- Installation of soil, meteorological and irrigation equipment.
- Design, installation and analysis of agricultural experiments under drip irrigation systems.

References: Prof. Dr. Eddie Schrevens, Prof. Dr. Guido Wyseure, Prof. Dr. Jan Diels

SEP 2013 -DEC 2018

Research Officer - VLIR/UOS-UNALM PROJECT, Junin - Peru

Sustainable Agriculture in the Central Peruvian Andes Subproject

- Leading the design, installation and evaluation of agricultural experiments under rainfed conditions.
- $Consolidation of rational \, databases, development \, of soil-crop-atmosphere \, models \, and \, advanced \, statistical \, techniques.$
- Analysis of agroecosystems using participatory approaches along with biophysical and biochemical assessments.

References: Prof. Dr. Eddie Schrevens, Prof. Dr. Sady García

FEB 2013 -APR 2019

Research Officer - VLIR/UOS-UNALM PROJECT, Junin | Lima - Peru

Drone Technology in Agriculture Subproject

- Leading the feasibility study for uses of drone technology in agroecosystems.
- $In charge \ of \ drone \ flights in \ Peruvian's \ Andes \ and \ Arid \ regions. \ Implementation \ of \ photogram metric \ and \ GIS \ databases.$
- Development of mathematical and statistical workflows for land use classification and field experiments' assessment.

References: Prof. Dr. Eddie Schrevens, MSc. Dries Raymaekers

JAN 2012 -DEC 2018

Research Officer - VLIR/UOS-UNALM PROJECT, Junin - Peru

18 Watersheds Management Subproject

- Leading the study of soil-crop-environment interactions and hydrology in the Peruvian Central Andes.
- Installation of soil, climatological and hydrometric equipment.
- Implementation of databases, application of hydrological models and assessment of rainfall-runoff relations.

References: Prof. Dr. Eduardo Chávarri, Prof. Dr. Guido Wyseure

Education

APR 2016 - PhD in Bioscience Engineering, Mechatronics, Biostatistics and Sensors - KU Leuven, Belgium

DEC 2019 Thesis Title: "Multi-target methodologies for the improvement of agricultural systems research

- Study cases at system and field level". | Advisor: Prof. Dr. Eddie Schrevens

JAN 2007 - **BSc in Agricultural Engineering**, *Water Resources* - Agrarian National University La Molina , Peru

DEC 2011 Honor Thesis Title: "Analysis of flood peaks in small Andean watersheds, Junin Department,

Peru (2011-2012 Period)". | Advisor: Prof. Dr. Eduardo Chávarri

Relevant Publications

- 1. **Grados, D.,** Butterbach-Bahl, K., Chen, J., Van Groenigen, K. J., Olesen, J., Van Groenigen, J. W., Abalos, D., 2022. Synthesizing the evidence of nitrous oxide mitigation practices in agroecosystems. *Environmental Research Letters*. https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/ac9b50.
- 2. **Grados, D.,** Reynafarje, X., Schrevens, E., 2020. A methodological approach to assess canopy NDVI–based tomato dynamics under irrigation treatments. *Journal of Agricultural Water Management*, 240, 106208. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agwat.2020.106208.
- 3. **Grados, D.,** García, S., Schrevens, E., 2020. Assessing the potato yield gap in the Peruvian Central Andes. *Journal of Agricultural Systems*, 181, 102817. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agsy.2020.102817.
- 4. **Grados, D.,** Schrevens, E., 2019. Multidimensional analysis of environmental impacts from potato agricultural production in the Peruvian Central Andes. *Science of The Total Environment*, 663, 927–934. http://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.01.414.

Relevant Conference Proceedings [PEER-REVIEWED]

- Grados, D., García, S., Schrevens, E., Nitrogen and water use efficiency under rain-fed potato agriculture: An experimental study. *Acta Horticulturae* (1253, 243–252). *International Symposium on Water and Nutrient Relations and Management of Horticultural Crops*, Istanbul, Turkey, 12-16 Aug 2018. http://doi.org/10.17660/actahortic.2019.1253.33.
- Grados, D., Vetters, E., Heuts, R., Schrevens, E., A model based technical sustainability analysis of potato production systems in the Mantaro Valley, Central Highlands, Peru. *Acta Horticulturae* (1154, 155-152). Symposium on Applications of Modelling as an Innovative Technology in the Horticultural Supply Chain, Wageningen, The Netherlands, 11-14 Oct 2015. http://doi.org/10.17660/actahortic.2017.1154.20.
- Grados, D., Vera, J., Schrevens, E., Corn-faba bean associations in the Peruvian Central Andes. *Acta Horticulturae* (1128, 79-88). *International Symposium on Horticulture in Developing Countries and World Food Production*, Brisbane, Australia, 19-22 Aug 2014. http://doi.org/10.17660/actahortic. 2016.1128.11.

Teaching Experience

- FA 2021 Carbon Cycling and Climate Change Master in Agrobiology, Aarhus University
 - Teacher Assistant: I guided students during the discussion and practical sessions to assess agroecosystems. I supported them on the development of their research papers. [10 students]
- FA 2017 Applied Multivariate Statistical Analysis Master in Bioscience Engineering, KU Leuven
 - Teacher Assistant: I taught students how to analyze their databases using statistical software by leading R-tutorials. I was responsible for the practical sessions on data wrangling and visualization, matrix algebra, R-programming and advanced multivariate techniques. [80 students]
- FA 2019 Biological Production Systems Bachelor in Bioscience Engineering, **KU Leuven**Teacher Assistant: I guided students during the discussion and practical sessions to assess agroecosystems.

 I taught them the essentials of process-based mathematical modelling and supported them on the development of their research papers. [25 students]
- SP 2016 Ecosystems Modelling Master in Bioscience Engineering, **KU Leuven**Teacher Assistant: I taught students how to develop and utilize agroecosystems models at diverse scales by leading R-tutorials. I guided the practical sessions on mathematical and statistical concepts, data wrangling and visualization, R-programming. I taught them the fundamental topics on process-based modelling of agroecosystems: identification, implementation, calibration and validation. [10 students]

Fellowships

- 2022 **Aarhus University** Travel Grant [400€] 2021 **iCLIMATE** Research Grant [3 600€]
- 2020 **FONDECYT-CONCYTEC** Research Grant [5 500€]
- 2016 2019 VLIR/UOS-UNALM PhD Fellowship [82 000€]
- 2013 | 2014 | 2015 VLIR/UOS-UNALM International Scholar Fellowships [67 000€]

Ad-Hoc Reviewer

Agronomy for Sustainable Development, Agricultural Systems, European Journal of Agronomy, Geoderma, Journal of Cleaner Production, Plant and Soil, Soil Use and Management.

Languages

English: Full professional proficiency Italian and Dutch: Elementary working proficiency French: Limited working proficiency Spanish: Native/Bilingual

Technical Skills

Programming R, Python, MATLAB
Markup Markdown, LATEX

Other RStudio, Spyder, Office, QGIS, GRASS GIS, Git/GitHub, HTML/CSS, Make, HPC